Guide to the James Hosmer Penniman Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1718-1944; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - Walters, Arthur J. to Sandham, Mrs. W.R., 1934 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 165)
    - Weare, Meshech to the Selectmen of Charlestown, 1728 July 6 (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Weare, Meshech to Hunt, Samuel, 1781 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Webster, Daniel (1782-1852) Autograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 167)
    - White, Andrew Dickson (1832-1918) to various correspondents, 1873-1899 (Box 2, Folder 167a)
    - Willcox, David to Schwab, John C., 1906 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 168)
    - Williams, George A. to Linsley, Miss, 1890 September 4 (Box 2, Folder 169)
    - Winslow, Hubbard (1799-1864) to Bowles, Samuel. (1797-1851), 1841 December 3 (Box 2, Folder 170)
    - Winsor, Justin (1831-1897) to Harrison, Mr. Robert, 1877 December 11 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - Woodward, Ashbel (1804-1885) to Unidentified, 1878 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 172)
    - Worcester, Joseph Emerson (1784-1865) to Aspinwall, Thomas, 1840 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - Yale University Secretary to Dana, Edward S., 1914 March 10 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Young Men's Clay Association, N.Y. City to Clay, Henry, 1846 December 7 (Box 2, Folder 175)
- Subject File, 1653-1944; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II contains articles relating to education as well as manuscripts of poems, a play and a Latin dictionary. Included also are autographs, an autograph book, a diary and some personal materials of J.H. Penniman.
  The Subject File is arranged alphabetically by subject or author.
  - Anthon, Charles (1797-1867). Manuscript of Latin dictionary?, undated (Box 3, Folder 176)
  - Article: "On Education" Author unidentified, 1789 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - Baker, Fred. Notes on how to raise money for Colby College, 1944 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - Brown, Solyman. Manuscript of poem, "The Sleeper Awakened", undated (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - Calixtus, George. Autograph, 1653 (Box 3, Folder 180)
  - Comedy (one-act): Cecilia or the Sacrifice of Friendship. Author unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 181)
  - Dana, James Dwight (1813-1895). MS of Article: "Our Next President" (Of Yale), 1871 June 24 (Box 3, Folder 182)
  - Ford, Hattie F. Diary and autographs, 1878-1882 (Box 3, Folder 183)
  - Hobson, Captain. Article: "Opportunities for Young Men in the Navy", [ca.1900] (Box 3, Folder 184)
  - Loring, Edward G.
    - Diagrams of progression of eye disease in scholars, undated (Box 3, Folder 185)
    - Review of Book: Statistics of Myopia and Hyperopia, undated (Box 3, Folder 185)
  - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle au Jardin du Roi Entrance ticket, undated (Box 3, Folder 186)
  - Newell, Timothy (1820-1901). Article: What Changes Does Psychology Demand in our School System?, undated (Box 3, Folder 187)
  - Penniman, James Hosmer
    - Autograph note, undated (Box 3, Folder 188)
    - Book Reviews (2), undated (Box 3, Folder 188)
    - Newspaper clipping of highway plan, 1929 August (Box 3, Folder 188)
  - Penniman, James Lanman. Account book for sophomore year, Yale College, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 188A)
  - Penniman, James Hosmer
    General note
    Security File, (Consult Head of Reader Services)
    - Clippings, 1926-1929, undated (Box 3, Folder 188B)
    - Autograph album, Circa 1875-1882
  - Spalding, James Alfred (1846- ?). Article: "Short Sight in Portland Schools", undated (Box 3, Folder 189)
  - Wordin, Eugene. Autograph Book., 1861-1866 (Box 3, Folder 190)
- Legal Papers, 1731-1837; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series III contains various legal documents pertaining to the American colonies and the early national period. These include warrants of arrest, bills, receipts, deeds, shareholder's certificates, the probate of a will, the transcript of a trial and an attorney's case. Also included is a letter of introduction from Metternich and a passport for traveling in France. Biographical information has been added to much of the material. Series III is arranged chronologically.
  - New Hampshire Justice's Court. Transcript of trial for counterfeiting., 1731/2 March 3 (Box 4, Folder 191)
  - William Smith. Deed of land ownership in New York City, 1733 June 28 (Box 4, Folder 192)
  - Haines, Samuel, Suffolk, N.Y. Inventory of his estate., 1741 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 193)
  - Ripley, Nathaniel, Windham, Conn. Warrant for arrest, owing debt to Caleb Turner, 1753 March 15 (Box 4, Folder 194)
  - Seven Years' War Privateering, New York, 1759 June 12 (Box 4, Folder 195)
  - Brownson, Josiah, and Johnson, William Samuel. I.O.U. with biographical information, 1759 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 196)
  - Buckingham, Gideon. Certificate of service to Army, with biographical information, signed by Nathaniel Clarke., 1756 January 19 (Box 4, Folder 197)
  - Wilberd, Richard. Probate of his will, signed by Mark Jenness, 1762 August 25 (Box 4, Folder 198)
  - Fairfield, Conn. Court Summons, 1762 October (Box 4, Folder 199)
  - Deed of property in Rochester, 1768 August 30 (Box 4, Folder 200)
  - Ward, Henry. Treasurer's Report, Colony of R.I. Reimbursement to Nathaniel Helme, 1770 July (Box 4, Folder 201)
  - Read, George (1733-1798) to Richard M. William, concerning guardians of children of Robert Alexander., 1772 January 9 (Box 4, Folder 202)
  - Howard Martin. Receipt, 1773 December 22 (Box 4, Folder 203)
  - Cartey, John, Colchester, Conn. New London Court Summons., 1774 May 26 (Box 4, Folder 204)
  - Davan, John, Essex County, N.J. Warrant of Confiscation, 1798 April (Box 4, Folder 205)
  - Union School House, New Haven, Conn. Shareholder's Certificates, 1802 (Box 4, Folder 206)
  - Lowell, Charles Lewis. Passport to travel in France, 1804 July 23 (Box 4, Folder 207)
  - Romilly, Sir Samuel (1757-1818). Attorney's case concerning partnership of Mr. Reed and Mr. Green, 1809 August 15 (Box 4, Folder 208)
  - Metternich-Winneburg, Clemens Wenzel Lothar. Letter of introduction for Dr. Ludwig Dürr, 1836 July 23 (Box 4, Folder 209)
  - Trustees of A.L. Seminary. Concerning boarding of Lathrop Family, 1837 April 1 (Box 4, Folder 210)
- Educational Materials, 1724, 1770-1903, 1948; Series IV; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Series IV is divided into two sections. The first section contains documents of various schools. These include petitions, charters, reports and certificates given to students. These documents are arranged chronologically with undated material at the end.
  The second section, "Books," includes textbooks, notebooks (mostly arithmetic notebooks) and study materials such as penmanship sheets. Also included is an Italian teaching manual. The books are arranged alphabetically by type. Within each type-category, they are arranged in chronological order with undated material at the end. The owner's names are also indicated.
  - Documents
    - Burton, Silas. School Rate for Oronoke District, 1795 (Box 4, Folder 211)
    - Wheeler, Thomas. Bill for tutoring children of William Reed, 1800 April 5 (Box 4, Folder 212)
    - Union School, New Haven, Conn. Photostats of Petitions, 1801 (Box 4, Folder 213)
    - Regulations for a school. Unidentified, [1810] (Box 4, Folder 214)
    - Sherman, Roger Minott. Paper on the Conn. School Fund, [1810] (Box 4, Folder 215)
    - Paris. Conseil Royal de l'Instruction Publique. Letter to M. Selvere, 1821 February 7 (Box 4, Folder 216)
    - Washington College, Hartford, Conn. Petition and Charter, 1823 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 217)
    - Oxford, Charles, Trinity College. Certificate of James Hesee's attendance at his classes, 1827 April 3 (Box 4, Folder 218)
    - Hopkinton, N.H. Citizens' Committee. Petition to the Senate and House of Representatives of N.H., 1836 (Box 4, Folder 219)
    - Seymour, Conn. School District No. 5. Secretary's minutes, 1841-1851 (Box 4, Folder 220)
    - Union College. Invitation to semi-centennial anniversary, 1845 July 22 (Box 4, Folder 221)
    - Eastern School, Northford, Conn. Records, 1846-[1855] (Box 4, Folder 222)
    - Cambridge University. Account with Francis Robinson, 1851 April (Box 4, Folder 223)
    - Eastern School, Northford, Conn. Todd Family certificates, 1851, 1856, 1861, undated (Box 4, Folder 224)
    - Fair Haven School Society, Board of Education. (Box 4, Folder 225)
    - Records of the Secretary, 1858-1871 (Box 4, Folder 225)
    - Account of the District Treasurer, 1862-1871 (Box 4, Folder 225)
  - Brooklyn Public School. Certificates of Merit to
    - Sammis, Leonora, 1859 June 5 (Box 4, Folder 226)
    - Sammis, Clarence, 1862 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 226)
  - Lisbon, Conn. Board of School Visitors. Annual Report, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 227)
  - Lisbon, Conn. School Board. Report, 1885-1886 (Box 4, Folder 228)
  - Lisbon, Conn. Board of Education. Report, 1888 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 229)
  - Price, J.W. Certificate of preliminary examination for admission into Harvard College, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 230)
  - Whitney, H.P. Certificate of admission to Harvard College, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 231)
  - New Haven University Extension Center. List of members, 1894, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 232)
  - Cambridge University. Certificate to Emmeline V. King for passing Senior Students' Exam, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 233)
  - Hotchkiss School, Lakeville, Conn. Report on Retiring Annuity Plan, 1948 November 15 (Box 5, Folder 234)
  - Orange Center School, Orange, Conn. Teachers' reports to the P.T.A., undated (Box 5, Folder 235)
  - Ladies of New Haven, led by Mrs. Eli Whitney. Petition that sewing instruction be restored in the schools., undated (Box 5, Folder 236)
  - Books
    - Arithmetic Notebooks:
      - Unidentifed, 1770 (Box 5, Folder 237)
      - Crane, Thirstin. First pages used as scrapbook for newspaper clippings (poems, jokes, etc.), [1785] (Box 5, Folder 238)
      - Wright, Elizur. Methods of Determining Areas, 1792 (Box 5, Folder 239)
      - Young, Thesden, 1794 (Box 5, Folder 240)
      - Unidentified, 1813 November (Box 5, Folder 241)
      - Purinton, Esther, [1820] (Box 5, Folder 242)
      - Knowles, John, 1823-1829 (Box 5, Folder 243)
      - Root, Charles. Arithmeticania, 1833 January 18 (Box 5, Folder 244)
      - Stark, William Henry [Daboll's Arithmetic], 1842 (Box 5, Folder 245)
      - Palmer, George, [1844] (Box 5, Folder 246)
      - Merriman, Mansfield. Continuous and Simple Girders: Their Mathematical Theory and Their Practical Calculation, 1875 (Box 6, Folder 247)
      - Book with the names on it of Benjamin Boardman, John Hall, John Devotion, James Hotchkiss, undated (Box 6, Folder 248)
      - Ford, Denis Smith, undated (Box 6, Folder 249)
      - Gorum, George, undated (Box 6, Folder 250)
    - Astronomy Notebook, with one-act Comedy in back. Unidentifed, undated (Box 6, Folder 251)
    - Bookkeeping Notebook. Unidentifed, 1837 (Box 6, Folder 252)
    - Bookkeeping Notebook. Chidsey, Ida M., 1887 October 26 (Box 6, Folder 253)
    - Ethnography (textbook) by Shillington, E., 1835 (Box 6, Folder 254)
  - Greek Grammar, or Busey's Improved, 1724 (Box 6, Folder 255)
  - Notebook of a Harvard student. Barron, Oliver, 1786 (Box 7, Folder 256)
  - Notebook with directions for knitting, window gardening, etc. Newell, Pomeroy, [1870] (Box 7, Folder 257)
  - Penmanship Materials
    - Scrap practice paper, 1785 April 28 (Box 7, Folder 258)
    - Notebook of Justus Palmer, [1822] (Box 7, Folder 259)
    - Poems, copied: "The Indian Warrior" (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - Poems, copied: "The Mus, or Love's Anguish", [1800] (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - Poem copied, and drawing. Van Cleve, J.W., 1825 (Box 7, Folder 261)
  - Surveying book. William, Henry, 1800 April 25 (Box 7, Folder 262)
  - Surveying and Geometry Notebook Hull. Lathrop W., 1819 (Box 7, Folder 263)
  - Teaching Manual for elementary school. Instruzioni Particolari Per la Direttrice dell'Asilo Infantile, undated (Box 7, Folder 264)
- David Francis Lincoln, 1871-1872, 1875-1878; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series is a miniature collection of materials relating to David Francis Lincoln's research and theories on education as well as problems of education in general. It is divided into three sections.
  The first section, "Correspondence," includes professional correspondence of D.F. Lincoln which largely concerns his theory of the "Half-time System" and descriptions of different school systems. Enclosed also are school infirmary charts and a report to the Board of Education. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author and then by recipient for each author.
  The second section includes Lincoln's notes on the "Half-time System," German and English schools and other aspects of education. The notes are arranged alphabetically by assigned subject titles. Excerpts and quotes are designated by the term "from" which precedes the name of the source.
  The third section includes manuscripts of two essays on education by Mr. Lincoln.
  - Correspondence
    - Apgar, Ellis A., 1877 August 24 (Box 8, Folder 265)
    - Baird, Jonathan, 1877 August 11 (Box 8, Folder 266)
    - Blake, C.J., with school infirmary charts, 1876 August 31 (Box 8, Folder 267)
    - Bradford, J.H., 1877 August 16 (Box 8, Folder 268)
    - Conant, Edward, 1877 August 20 (Box 8, Folder 269)
    - Cortrell, William, 1877 August 24 (Box 8, Folder 270)
    - Daelman, J., 1877 September 3 (Box 8, Folder 271)
    - Davis, N., 1877 January 1 (Box 8, Folder 272)
    - F., M., Karlsruh, translation of letter into English, 1877 November 30 (Box 8, Folder 273)
    - Goodell, A.H., 1877 August 15 (Box 8, Folder 274)
    - Goodwin, C., 1877 August 6 (Box 8, Folder 275)
    - Gregory, J.M., 1877 August 18 (Box 8, Folder 276)
    - H., E., Prussia, translation of letter into English, 1877 November 16 (Box 8, Folder 277)
    - Hale, A., 1877 October 1 (Box 8, Folder 278)
    - Hanson, James, 1878 January 14 (Box 8, Folder 279)
    - Harrington, Henry F., 1878 January 5, 1878 January 15 (Box 8, Folder 280)
    - Harris, 1878 January 12 (Box 8, Folder 281)
    - Hobee, John, 1877 August 18 (Box 8, Folder 282)
    - Hovell, Henry, 1877 August 10 (Box 8, Folder 283)
    - Jones, A.P., 1878 February 6 (Box 8, Folder 284)
    - Keyes, Addison A., 1877 August 9 (Box 8, Folder 285)
    - Level, William D., 1877 August 9 (Box 8, Folder 286)
    - Lewis, A.H., 1877 October 30, 1877 November 10
      - Report to Board of Education, 1876 February 7 (Box 8, Folder 287)
    - Lincoln, D.F. to (Box 8, Folder 288)
      - Apgar, Ellis A., 1877 August 7 (Box 8, Folder 288)
      - Chadwick, Edwin, 1877 September 22 (Box 8, Folder 288)
      - Downs, Charles A., 1877 August 14 (Box 8, Folder 288)
      - Varrentrapp, George, 1877 October 9 (Box 8, Folder 288)
    - Lyman, Theodore, 1877 August 26 (Box 8, Folder 289)
    - Newell, I., 1877 August 17 (Box 8, Folder 290)
    - Pickard, J., 1877 August 20 (Box 8, Folder 291)
    - Russell., A.H., 1877 August 30 (Box 8, Folder 292)
    - Small, Aug. D., 1878 January 14 (Box 8, Folder 293)
    - Soldan, L., 1877 August 13 (Box 8, Folder 294)
    - Spalding, James Alfred (1846-), 1876 September 4 (Box 8, Folder 295)
    - Stockwell, Thomas B., 1877 August 11 (Box 8, Folder 296)
    - Strange, William, 1877 August 10 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Varrentrapp, W. George, 1877 November 1, 1877 December 11 (Box 8, Folder 298)
    - Wey, William C., 1877 October 18, 1877 November 1 (Box 8, Folder 299)
    - Wilder, B.P., 1877 September 1 (Box 8, Folder 300)
    - Winsor, F., n.y. September 17 (Box 8, Folder 301)
    - Wood, William, 1877 August 13, 1877 October 19 (Box 8, Folder 302)
  - Notes
    - on Advisable number of school hours, undated (Box 8, Folder 303)
    - from Apgar, E.A. (Box 8, Folder 304)
    - on Boston school children, 1877 January 31 (Box 8, Folder 305)
    - from Chadwick, E., 1877 (Box 8, Folder 306)
    - from Compendium of Census of Mass., 1875 (Box 8, Folder 307)
    - on Compulsory Education, undated (Box 8, Folder 308)
    - from Curwen, John's report, 1875 (Box 8, Folder 309)
    - on Dalton, Charle's report on Indian Orchard Mills, undated (Box 8, Folder 310)
    - on English education system, 1872 January (Box 8, Folder 311)
    - on Factory work with schooling, undated (Box 8, Folder 312)
    - on German schools, undated (Box 8, Folder 313)
    - from Goodwin, C.S.; Whitaker, John, 1871, undated (Box 8, Folder 314)
    - Half-time System, questions formulae, undated (Box 8, Folder 315)
    - from Leach, Daniel, undated (Box 8, Folder 316)
    - List of correspondents, undated (Box 8, Folder 317)
    - on London School Board by-laws, 1871 November 15 (Box 8, Folder 318)
    - on Loring Lothrop's report, undated (Box 8, Folder 319)
    - on Manchester School laws, undated (Box 8, Folder 320)
    - on Model School, Glasgow, undated (Box 8, Folder 321)
    - on Naumkesy Half-time School, Salem, undated (Box 8, Folder 322)
    - from Phibrick's report, 1872 (Box 8, Folder 323)
    - on Recommendations by Bureau of Labor, 1872 (Box 8, Folder 324)
    - Referral by Durgin, S.H. of Jones, Israel, 1877 August 28 (Box 8, Folder 325)
    - on Rice School, undated (Box 8, Folder 326)
    - on St. Mark's School, undated (Box 8, Folder 327)
    - on Schools in states of U.S.A., undated (Box 8, Folder 328)
    - on Sigmund, Mr., undated (Box 8, Folder 329)
    - on Standard of Attainment, undated (Box 8, Folder 330)
    - on Study of German in public schools, undated (Box 8, Folder 331)
    - from Teacher's Circular, undated (Box 8, Folder 332)
    - on West Point regulations, undated (Box 8, Folder 333)
    - from Wood, William (Box 8, Folder 334)
  - Manuscripts
    - Lecture: "The Half-time System in Education" manuscript, galleys, newspaper clippings, 1877 September 7 (Box 8, Folder 335)
    - Report on School Hygiene, 1876 September 8 (Box 8, Folder 336)
- Engravings, 1888; Series VI; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series includes a cartoon, engravings and photographs of men whose correspondence are included in Series I. Engravings are entered alphabetically under the name of the individual pictured.
  - Abd-el-Kader, undated (Box 8, Folder 337)
  - Abbott, John Stevens Cabot (with autograph), undated (Box 8, Folder 338)
  - Bigelow, John; Page, Thomas Nelson (photograph), undated (Box 8, Folder 339)
  - Brown, Solyman, undated (Box 8, Folder 340)
  - Burritt, Elihu, undated (Box 8, Folder 341)
  - Clay, Henry - on cloth [bookmark], undated (Box 8, Folder 342)
  - Clay, Henry and Daniel Webster (cartoon), undated (Box 8, Folder 343)
  - Read, George, undated (Box 8, Folder 344)
  - Landon, Melville de Lancey (newspaper photo), 1888 October (Box 8, Folder 345)
  - Mackintosh, Sir James, undated (Box 8, Folder 346)
  - Mahan, Alfred Thayer, undated (Box 8, Folder 347)
  - Nadaillac, Jean F. (Marquis de) (photograph), undated (Box 8, Folder 348)
  - Smith, William, undated (Box 8, Folder 349)
  - Worcester College, Oxford University, undated (Box 8, Folder 350)
  - Worcester, J.E., undated (Box 8, Folder 351)